<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="rules">
  <title>Game rules</title>

  <section>
    <title>Object of the game</title>

    <para>Your duty is to use your army to conquer countries, eventually whole
    continents and fulfil the mission. The mission depends on the game type
    you play, of which there are three:</para>

    <para>Secret Mission - this is the classic and most-played game type. You
    (and your opponents of course as well) get a mission you have to comply.
    Missions range from conquering two or three continents to the elimination
    of a single opponent.</para>

    <para>World Domination - as the name states, you have to defeat all your
    enemies and conquer the whole world.</para>

    <para>Capital - The same rules as world domination; but you don't have to
    conquer the whole world: Only the capital countries have to get under your
    control.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Basic rules</title>

    <para>On your turn, try to capture territories by defeating your
    opponents' armies. But be careful: Winning battles will depend on careful
    planning, quick decisions and bold moves. You?ll have to place your forces
    wisely, attack at just the right time and fortify your defenses against
    all enemies.</para>

    <para>Each of your turns consists of three steps, in this order:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Getting and placing new armies</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Attacking, if you choose to, by rolling the dice</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Fortifying your position</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Getting and placing new armies</title>

      <para>At the beginning of each turn, calculate how many new armies
      you'll add to your territories based on:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The number of territories you occupy</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The value of the continents you control</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The value of the matched sets of RISK cards you trade
          in</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The specific territory pictured on a traded-in card</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The above 4 steps is automatically calculated by the game and it
      will display how many armies you can place for that turn.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Territories</title>

        <para>At the beginning of every turn (including your first), count the
        number of territories you currently occupy, then divide the total by
        three (ignore any fraction). The answer is the number of armies you
        receive. Place the new armies on any territory you already
        occupy.</para>

        <example>
          <title>Your territory and your new army</title>

          <para>11 territories = 3 armies</para>

          <para>14 territories = 4 armies</para>

          <para>17 territories = 5 armies</para>
        </example>

        <para>You will always receive at least 3 armies on a turn, even if you
        occupy fewer than 9 territories.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Continents</title>

        <para>In addition, at the beginning of your turn you will receive
        armies for each continent you control. (To control a continent, you
        must occupy all its territories at the start of your turn.) </para>

        <para>To find the exact number of armies you'll receive for each
        continent, look at the chart in the lower left-hand corner of the game
        board.</para>

        <para><table>
            <title>Continent values of the classic board</title>

            <tgroup cols="2">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>North America</entry>

                  <entry>5</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>South America</entry>

                  <entry>2</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Europe</entry>

                  <entry>5</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Africa</entry>

                  <entry>3</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Asia</entry>

                  <entry>7</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Australia</entry>

                  <entry>2</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Risk cards</title>

        <section>
          <title>Earning Cards</title>

          <para>At the end of any turn in which you have captured at least one
          territory, you will earn one (and only one) Risk card. You are
          trying to collect sets of 3 cards in any of the following
          combinations:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>3 cards of same design (3 Infantry or 3 Cavalry or 3
              Artillery)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>1 each of 3 designs (1 Infantry + 1 Cavalry + 1
              Artillery)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Any two + 1 "wildcard" (card with all three symbols on
              it)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>If you have collected a set of 3 Risk cards, you may turn them
          in at the beginning of your next turn, or you may wait. But if you
          have 5 or 6 cards at the beginning of your turn, you must trade in
          at least one set, and may trade in a second set if you have
          one.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Trading In Cards for Armies</title>

          <para>At the beginning of subsequent turns, you may trade in matched
          sets of cards and take additional armies based on the total number
          of sets anyone has traded in so far. The game will show you the
          value of the next set to be traded in.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The first set traded in - 4 armies</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The second set traded in - 6 armies</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The third set traded in - 8 armies</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The fourth set traded in - 10 armies</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The fifth set traded in - 12 armies</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The sixth set traded in - 15 armies</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>After the sixth set has been traded in, each additional set is
          worth 5 more armies. Example: If you trade in the seventh set, you
          get 20 armies; if you trade in the eighth, you get 25 armies, and so
          on. "First" and "second" set, etc., refer to sets traded in by
          anyone during the game. Thus, if you trade in the third set in the
          game, you receive 8 armies, even if it's the first set you have
          traded in.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Occupied territories</title>

          <para>If any of the 3 cards you trade in shows the picture of a
          territory you occupy, you receive 2 extra armies. You must place
          both those armies onto that particular territory.</para>

          <note>
            <para>On a single turn, you may receive no more than 2 extra
            armies above and beyond those you receive for the matched sets of
            cards you trade in.</para>
          </note>

          <para>Hint: No matter how many armies you receive at the start of
          your turn, deploy them carefully-either to prepare for an attack or
          to defend against one. It is good military strategy to move your
          armies to the front, heavily fortifying territories that border
          enemy territories.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Attacking</title>

      <para>After placing your armies at the beginning of your turn, decide if
      you wish to attack at this time. The object of an attack is to capture a
      territory by defeating all the opposing armies already on it. The battle
      is fought by a roll of the dice. Study the board for a moment. Do you
      want to attack?</para>

      <para>If you choose not to attack, pass the dice to the player on your
      left. You may still fortify your position, if you wish.</para>

      <para>If you choose to attack, you must follow these rules:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You may only attack a territory that's adjacent (touching) to
          one of your own, or connected to it by a dashed line.</para>

          <example>
            <title>Touching territories</title>

            <para>Greenland may attack the Northwest Territory, Ontario,
            Quebec and Iceland. North Africa may attack Egypt, Western Europe
            and Brazil. At the western and eastern edges of the board, Alaska
            is considered adjacent to, and may attack, Kamchatka.</para>
          </example>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You must always have at least two armies in the territory
          you're attacking from.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You may continue attacking one territory until you have
          eliminated all armies on it, or you may shift your attack from one
          territory to another, attacking each as often as you like and
          attacking as many territories as you like during one turn.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <section>
        <title>To attack</title>

        <para>First announce both the territory you're attacking and the one
        you're attacking from. Then roll the dice against the opponent who
        occupies the opposing territory.</para>

        <para>Before rolling, both you and your opponent must announce the
        number of dice you intend to roll, and you both must roll at the same
        time.</para>

        <para>You, the attacker, will roll 1,2 or 3 red dice: You must have at
        least one more army in your territory than the number of dice you
        roll. Hint: The more dice you roll, the greater your odds of winning.
        Yet the more dice you roll, the more armies you may lose, or be
        required to move into a captured territory.</para>

        <para>The defender will roll either 1 or 2 white dice: To roll 2 dice,
        he or she must have at least 2 armies on the territory under attack.
        Hint: The more dice the defender rolls, the greater his or her odds of
        winning - but the more armies he or she may lose.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>To Decide a Battle</title>

        <para> Compare the highest die each of you rolled. If yours (the
        attacker's) is higher, the defender loses one army from the territory
        under attack. But if the defender's die is higher than yours, you lose
        one army from the territory you attacked from; put it back in your
        clear plastic box. If each of you rolled more than one die, now
        compare the two next-highest dice and repeat the process.</para>

        <note>
          <para>In case of a tie, the defender always wins. </para>

          <para>The attacker can never lose more than 2 armies on a single
          roll.</para>
        </note>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Capturing territories</title>

        <para>As soon as you defeat the last opposing army on a territory, you
        capture that territory and must occupy it immediately. To do so, move
        in at least as many armies as the number of dice you rolled in your
        last battle.</para>

        <para>Remember: In most cases, moving as many armies as you can to the
        front is advantageous, because armies left behind can't help you when
        you are attacking.</para>

        <para>Also remember you must always leave at least one army behind on
        the territory you attacked from.</para>

        <para>During the game, every territory must always be occupied by at
        least one army.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Ending your attack</title>

        <para>You may end your attack(s) at any time. If you have captured at
        least one territory, you will be awarded 1 Risk card. Your last step
        is to fortify your position, if you wish.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Eliminating an opponent</title>

        <para>If during your turn you eliminate an opponent by defeating his
        or her last army on the game board, you win any RISK cards that player
        has collected.</para>

        <para>If winning them gives you 6 or more cards, you must immediately
        trade in enough sets to reduce your hand to 4 or fewer cards, but once
        your hand is reduced to 4,3, or 2 cards, you must stop trading.</para>

        <para>But if winning them gives you fewer than 6, you must wait until
        the beginning of your next turn to trade in a set.</para>

        <note>
          <para>When you draw a card from the deck at the end of your turn
          (for having won a battle), if this brings your total to 6, you must
          wait until your next turn to trade in.</para>
        </note>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fortifying your position</title>

      <para>No matter what you've done on your turn, you may, if you wish, end
      your turn by fortifying your position. You are not required to win a
      battle or even to try an attack to do so. Some players refer to this as
      the "free move".</para>

      <para>To fortify your position, move as many armies as you'd like from
      one (and only one) of your territories into one (and only one) of your
      adjacent territories. Remember to move troops towards borders where they
      can help in an attack!</para>

      <para>In moving your armies from one territory to another, you must
      leave at least one army behind.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Winning</title>

      <para>The winner is the first player to fulfil his mission, dependent on
      the type of game you're playing.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Secret Mission</title>

    <section>
      <title>Object of the game</title>

      <para>To be the first player to complete the Mission described on your
      own Mission card. </para>

      <para>This game is suitable for from 3 to 6 players.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Equipment</title>

      <para>Use all the equipment of the World Domination game, plus the 12
      Mission cards. These cards give each player a different mission; when
      that mission has been completed, that player automatically wins the
      game.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Initial army placement</title>

      <para>Select a color and, depending on the number of players, count out
      the "armies" you'll need to start the game.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If 2 are playing, see instructions on Two Player Risk</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If 3 are playing, each player counts out 35 Infantry.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If 4 are playing, each player counts out 30 Infantry.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If 5 are playing, each player counts out 25 Infantry.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If 6 are playing, each player counts out 20 Infantry.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setup</title>

      <para>Before play begins, elect one player to be the General. If fewer
      than 6 are playing, the General removes the Mission cards that refer to
      the unused colors.</para>

      <para>The General shuffles the Mission cards and, starting to the left,
      deals one card face down to each player. The remaining Mission cards are
      put back in the box; no one, including the General, may look at
      them.</para>

      <para>The General removes the 2 Wild Cards from the deck of RISK cards,
      shuffles, and deals out all the cards, starting with the player to the
      left. (In a 4- or 5-player game, 2 players will each receive one extra
      card.) These cards determine which territories each of you will occupy
      at the beginning of the game.</para>

      <para>Each player places one army on each of his or her territories.
      When you've done this, go around the table in turn, placing another army
      on each of your territories. There is no limit to the number of armies
      that can occupy a single territory. Continue until all troops have been
      deployed across the map.</para>

      <para>The General now collects the RISK cards, replaces the 2 Wild
      Cards, shuffles the deck, and puts it to the side, face down.</para>

      <para>Game play continues as in the standard rules.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Winning</title>

      <para>The player who completes his or her mission first - and reveals
      the Mission card to prove it - wins.</para>

      <para>Important note: In Secret Mission RISK, it is possible that you
      will accomplish your mission with the aid (usually unintentional) of
      another player. For example, if your mission is to destroy all the
      yellow troops and another player actually removes the final yellow
      armies from the board, that player has helped you complete your Secret
      Mission.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>World Domination</title>

    <section>
      <title>Object of the game</title>

      <para>To conquer the world by occupying every territory on the board,
      thus eliminating all your opponents.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Initial Army Placement</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>If 2 are playing, see instructions on Two Player Risk</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If 3 are playing, each player counts out 35 Infantry.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If 4 are playing, each player counts out 30 Infantry.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If 5 are playing, each player counts out 25 Infantry.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If 6 are playing, each player counts out 20 Infantry.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setup</title>

      <para>Roll one die. Whoever rolls the highest number takes one Infantry
      piece from his or her pile and places it onto any territory on the
      board, thus claiming that territory.</para>

      <para>Starting to the left of the first player, everyone in turn places
      one army onto any unoccupied territory. Continue until all 42
      territories have been claimed.</para>

      <para>After all 42 territories are claimed, each player in turn places
      one additional army onto any territory he or she already occupies.
      Continue in this way until everyone has run out of armies. There is no
      limit to the number of armies you may place onto a single
      territory.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Completing the setup</title>

      <para>Shuffle the pack of RISK cards (remove the Mission cards) and
      place it, face down, by the side of the board. This pack forms the draw
      pile. This is done automatically by the game and you will be handed
      cards when necessary.</para>

      <para>Whoever placed the first army takes the first turn.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Winning</title>

      <para>The winner is the first player to eliminate every opponent by
      capturing all territories on the map.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Capital</title>

    <para>Read the complete World Domination rules first.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Object of the game</title>

      <para>To capture all opposing Headquarters-while still controlling your
      own territory.</para>

      <para>If you wish, you may shorten the game even further:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>4 players: Capture any 2 opposing Headquarters while
          controlling your own.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>5 or 6 players: Capture any 3 opposing Headquarters while
          controlling your own.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Equipment</title>

      <para>Same as in World Domination Risk. Remember to remove the Secret
      Mission cards.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setup</title>

      <para>After deploying your armies at the beginning of the game, select
      one of the territories you?ve claimed and make it your Headquarters.
      Then, without revealing the territory you?ve chosen, find its matching
      RISK card and place it face down in front of you.</para>

      <para>After everyone in turn has selected a Headquarters, all players
      turn their cards face up, thus revealing the location of their
      Headquarters.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Playing</title>

      <para>All World Domination Risk Rules apply, with these additions: If
      you capture an opposing Headquarters, place the Headquarters card you?ve
      won face up in front of you to prove you've captured it.</para>

      <para>If at any point your Headquarters is captured by an opponent, you
      are not eliminated from the game. Simply give your card to that opponent
      and continue playing.</para>

      <para>You may not use a Headquarters card as part of a matched set of
      RISK cards. Be sure to keep all Headquarters cards out of the way during
      the game.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Hints and Tips</title>

    <para>In all the RISK games, keep these 3 strategy hints in mind as you
    play, add armies, and fortify:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Conquer whole continents: You will earn more armies that way.
        (This doesn't apply in Secret Mission Risk.)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Watch your enemies: If they are building up forces on adjacent
        territories or continents, they may be planning an attack.
        Beware!</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Fortify borders adjacent to enemy territories for better defense
        if a neighbor decides to attack you.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>